I'm actually just got out of a really
fantastic conversation and wanted to
shoot a quick recording of one of the
notions that got some clarity I
apologize if I'm actually repeating
myself I've really frankly lost track of
most of what has been said in these
videos but this is interesting enough
that it's it bears repeating and I'm
certain I'll say it differently so if
you're familiar with a philosopher named
Conte he made a distinction between what
he called the numeral and phenomenal the
numeral is reality such as it actually
is and phenomenal is that thing which we
can actually ever under any
circumstances actually be in
relationship with perceptually so you
know look out the window and I see a
tree in point of fact all I'm able to
really say about it is that I the way
that my eyes perceive light and the way
that light relates to tree at least
under my understanding of physics and
optics generates the notion that there's
a tree there but in some deep
fundamental way I can't ever actually
have direct access to its Newman 'el
essence so what I want to do is I
actually talk about this fact as being a
fact of reality but it's actually more
important than just an interesting
observation because it creates an
intrinsic gap and that intrinsic gap is
what's interesting so if you imagine
this notion of the Newman --all and then
the notion of the phenomenal what one of
the the critiques of Conte that was
actually quite nice is evolution seems
to actually work by the process of
giving us feedback from the Newman all
itself which is to say this the sad look
in front of me and I'm taking a walk and
I noticed that there's a very deep hole
that leads to jagged rocks now this is a
phenomenal observation I am phenomenally
experiencing something that I can
describe to you as such however if I
fall into the hole and die that fact the
fact of my death is in fact a Newman
--all event now of course is it the
sediment that I can't actually
experience at all phenomenon but
evolution
which proceeds by Fitness which is in
fact actually just a cashing out of the
degree to which the noumenon phenomena
reinforced choices made by phenomenal
agents is a very interesting dynamic so
I actually have is a relationship I have
the relationship of what is actually
happening at the noumenon level and I
have a relationship of what is perceived
to be the case at the phenomenal level
which now I'm proposing is in fact an
ontological gap that gap is just going
to exist . but it's a gap that actually
has a really interesting relationship
it's not that the numeral it's kind of
exists out in nowhere space that we can
kind of think about if we are interested
in being German philosophers it's a way
of naming that thing which we can't ever
fully comprehend or perceive but
nonetheless actually is the cashing out
of how we interrelate with that which
exists so so then we talked about how
that shows up in terms of how we make
choices we have a problematic which is
we are always going to be operating with
one's some sort of sense making schema
this is the phenomenal all right the
phenomenal is the sense making we're
experiencing phenomena and we're
endeavoring to make sense of it so that
we can make better choices our choices
are then going to involve actions that
go into the new malaria are going to
cash out through the noumenon channel in
the actual fitness that it shows up for
right and so this is how we end up in
this really interesting problem space or
opportunity space which is let's say I
have a situation where I am making a
choice based upon my phenomenal
heuristics that is ultimately a bad
choice right now here's where we talk
about something like say being in
delusion delusion is when you end up
choosing to connect with and hold the
integrity of your phenomenal schema your
sense making framework rather than
allowing it to change under more
fundamental feedback from the new
mine'll now I'm now one may wonder how
is it the one goes about actually ever
perceiving that more fundamental
feedback from the Newman 'el and this is
actually subject of a different
conversation which we might call
intelligence and depth which I think
also is a very interesting thing that I
talked about two days ago let's talk
about some other interesting things so
we are always going to be faced ah sorry
the language of wants and needs so you
you want at the level of the the surface
of your phenomenal schema you need at
the level of depth and then there's
something that is in fact below what you
need which is the numeral but you will
be able to perceive that Newman 'el
precisely through the degree to which it
cascades up your needs and they'll give
you a concrete example let's say that
you you you feel thirsty alright so
what's happening is think about the
stack of sense making frameworks that
are actually handing this notion up you
feel thirsty what would that really
means is that you have some sense of say
your lips are dry which for mine art or
a sense that your eyes are dry or a
sense of just being low-energy or a
sense of something that you have begun
the process of constructing a way of
making sense of that you now name as
being thirst you know on top of that
you're then going to have a higher-order
schema which is okay how do you respond
to it now let's say you've got a
dysfunctional let's say your your senses
I'm thirty therefore I'm going to drink
a coke my villain of the moment that
actual turns out to be a bad choice
making schema right I've got a sense
making framework that is in fact
accurately telling me I'm thirsty but
the sense making schema that's on top of
that is saying actually I want a coke
alright so once and needs actually have
a whole space in between them and the
one space is the connection between
sense and choice want is ah okay what I
want is what toys do I make and senses
what needed my trying to fulfill and as
we've mentioned in the past one of the
problems we face with human as humans is
were really bad at that gap like we were
really really bad at being able to
connect good choice making to good
which is they were really bad at
connecting your watch to our needs but
now I'm gonna describe the needs
structure and more depth because what
happens is this so I sense that I'm
thirsty well well what's happening they
were switch what's actually happening is
something more along the lines of there
is an actual presence in my body of an
inadequacy of h2o molecules well what
does that mean what's actually happening
there is there's an actual presence in
my body of an inadequacy of the
appropriate substrate components for
well functioning metabolism at the level
of mitochondria for example what's
happening there right what's happening
there is the huh Bo static feedback
systems that are necessary for the well
functioning of my adaptive strategies in
my environment are being pushed out of
of optimality well finally what's
happening there is I'm becoming less fit
right and so now we've looped all the
way from the phenomenal to the noumenon
thing I'm becoming less fit as being
parsed it micro micro levels kind of was
that called leveraging up or trim
tabbing up from super sensitive
components that are probably billions of
years old
you know ATP systems not getting the
resource flow that they needed and
sensors that are indicating that and
upregulating it all the way up to my you
know choice making human that is going
out and buying a can of coke open go
glug-glug
so now we have this really interesting
concept right we've got an ocean now the
way that the numeral fits in
relationship to the phenomenal the way
this phenomenal has a relationship
between choice making is the feedback
from the phenomenal to the numeral the
making choice i buy a coke I'm not
connecting physical reality and then
shifting my state in actual luminal
reality whatever it is which then cycles
all the way back around and through this
micro micro room record trick a big
thing to how it actually cashes out no
okay it turns out by making the
continuing choice to drink coke I'm not
satisfying the actual underlying needs
for fitness I'm becoming less fit and
something happens in this case maybe I
die and of course now fam evolution is
now sent a very very strong signal to
the thing that used to be me there that
any good choices
removed whatever you know huge
gigantic genetic at
genetic emotional cognitive phenomenal
thing that was me from at least the
thing that evolution is pushing well I
could go all over the place after that
but I think that's that he will stop
there and yeah that that's think it